if you've noticed over the last few
years video on the internet especially
YouTube looks so much better than it
used to and a lot of that reason is cuz
people are shooting in 10 bit log so it
doesn't matter how nice of a camera you
bought if you're not shooting log you're
probably giving up a ton of image
quality So today we're going to talk
about the correct workflow in Final Cut
Pro to get all that image quality out of
your log footage still have tons of
flexibility to color grade it and if you
want make it look cinematic in the end
we're going to be using appal cuz ever
since that was added to the iPhone 15
Pro it massively improved what you can
get out of a cell phone it still blows
me away and you can match it to other
cameras so this workflow Works
regardless of what your camera is Canon
Sony Fuji Lumix doesn't matter this is
the way to work with log footage in
Final Cut Pro as quickly as possible I'm
going to explain log to anybody that
hasn't worked with it before it's not
the codec that's prores or h265 HC
things like that log is a color profile
and basically it looks like this it
looks completely flat and this is just a
way of preserving a lot more data and
therefore flexibility in your image by
removing the saturation and contrast a
very loose analogy or I guess the effect
of it is similar to shooting Raw photos
it preserves all of that flexibility so
that the image isn't baked in but the
problem is raw video is really huge so
log preserves that flexibility in a more
compressed format there's a lot more to
it but you don't need to know it to work
with it so let's dig into a timeline
here this is a bunch of footage from the
Calgary stamped I've just kind of thrown
it in the timeline I haven't done much
editing to it but as you can see it
already looks normal this basically
looks like iPhone footage you know
contrasty nice it's not what we're here
for we want to look better than this and
the fact that it looks normal is
actually just a trick of Final Cut Pro
if we reveal it in browser right click
again and reveal it in finder this is
what it looks like this is what you see
when you record it on your phone there's
no saturation no contrast so what's
happening in the background here is
final cut is applying a l and it's doing
a really good job like what blows me
away is this footage matches an iPhone
so well even though it was shot in log
it just kind of strips away the
oversharpening and stuff so over here in
the inspector we're going to scroll down
click on settings this is where we're
going to find various metadata settings
a whole bunch of stuff is in here
specifically camera L appal you can see
it just detected what the footage is and
if I turn it off we go back to our flat
no contrast image so I could do that one
clip at a time instead I'm going to go
over here to the browser and select
everything in this whole project go to
camera L and turn it off and now before
we get too far I've also got to point
out that we're going to be grading in
standard dynamic range not HDR High
dynamic range is the default on most
phones and that's actually what appal
log is capturing in but it's not
supported by a lot of apps it's a much
more complicated workflow and it's just
harder to grade it well like it's easy
to kind of make mistakes so we're going
to be working in SDR workflow which is
just still the most most common used by
most creators today so what we want to
do is go over here to color space
override right now it says that it's off
but it's actually defaulting to rec 2020
even though it's not telling us because
it's not overriding anything we want to
override it to rec 709 that is the
standard dynamic range color space so
when your timeline looks like this all
flat and boring what I think a lot of
people are tempted to do is select a
clip they're going to go over here their
color correction tools and they're
probably going to turn up the overall
saturation of the image start messing
with the contrast turn down those blacks
turn up the white Point let's turn on
some of our visualizations see what's
going on this is going totally off the
rails okay maybe like that uh you know
like we're sort of getting a normal-ish
image but never do this please don't do
this it is the most common mistake and
you can never get reliable results log
is created to be transformed in a
scientific prec prce way there are tools
to get much closer so you don't want to
rely on your own eyeballs to try to get
it there you want a good L now I'm going
to be using my L but you got to take my
word for it that I'm not making this
video just to sell my L there's others
out there you can go find a good one
there's plenty Google it if you want I
like mine there's a link to it below if
you want but there are many different
ways to find a good lot just find one
that looks good to you because the
built-in one from Apple is meant to look
like a normal iPhone so if you want the
same results I'm going to have here you
can try out mine but I'm not here to
sell it to you you can use whatever you
like and it's going to be the same
workflow so let's clear away those messy
changes and let's do it the right way
now everything looks flat and boring the
whole timeline but we're going to start
with just one clip work on that first
then we're going to expand it to the
rest and start off by opening your
effects browser click on color this is
the next most important step people get
this wrong all the time even if you know
how to use a l okay so we're going to
put a custom L on here just drag it over
onto the clip that we're going to be
working on a new feature in Final Cut Is
labeling your effects so let's call this
Apple log transform just to stay
organized and let's pretend we've never
added a l before so you're going to
click that drop down say choose custom l
in your finder you'll navigate to the ls
you've downloaded select them and now
here they are available in our dropdown
so I'm going to select appal to rec709
and now we're getting somewhere this
looks like proper footage if you want a
bit of a comparison here's a similar
clip using the Apple transform so this
is the default what you get out of
camera here it is with my L it's a bit
thicker kind of punchier but if that's
all you could do with log you wouldn't
be watching this tutorial here's where
the magic happens you need to make all
of your changes before that log
transform happens so you're going to
select color wheels drop them on here as
well and this is what's most important
the changes all need to happen before
the transform you see that so I'm gonna
actually I'm gonna turn the transform
off I'm going to call this primaries
meaning where I make the biggest changes
like exposure and white balance and if
you go into them you really can't tell
what I'm doing if you move them around
like this but it needs to be happening
on this flat version of the image let's
look at a demonstration there's a lot of
dynamic range going on this clip
specifically if we look at the sky here
it's pretty much blown out so let's
pretend we just wanted to expose for the
sky we could bring those highlights back
and you see we're actually recovering
quite a lot of detail here that's pretty
good and that's because the prime Aries
the adjustments were happening before
the long transform now let's copy those
adjustments paste them into another clip
right next to it and now we'll just move
those primaries afterwards look at the
difference here we really lose all of
that detail in the sky like you can even
see it in the waveform here there are
supposed to be lights in the sky over
there and they're fully recovered if
you're grading the log footage but if
you're grading after it's logged like
you're just grading the re 709 you can't
recover nearly as much of a difference
like check out trying to recover the
blue if I open up primaries after the
transform and I crank up the saturation
that's what it looks like now let's go
to the primaries
before look at all that blue there's so
much data there this is why you shoot
log like this is how you recover the
data don't even bother shooting log if
you're going to adjust it after you've
transformed it so let's do some quick
color grading in the primaries I'll
usually control exposure in my midtones
here if I was to affect the white
balance usually I'm doing that in the
midtones I don't actually love using
these temperature sliders cuz see how it
hits the highlights and the Shadows a
bit too much most of color temperature
really lives in the midtones here this
all basic color grading stuff so I'm not
going to go any further with it but you
might also want to add uh let's go into
color again uh some Hue saturation
curves another way to do that is
actually up here if you're like in your
editing area you can also add correction
there a bunch to choose from here again
Hue saturation curves I use all the time
you can use whatever you want but these
come in handy a lot and again I'm going
to make sure that that is happening
before the transform so we've got one
clip mostly ready to go but we've got a
whole timeline to edit here how do we do
that I'll show you in one second but
first I want to show you this crazy AI
tool that really speeds up your editing
like for real I'm using it to edit this
video I've been using it a lot of my
recent YouTube videos it's called gling
and it's kind of amazing if you ever
edit yourself talking it's just the best
way to do it so I recorded a little demo
here to show you I've already dropped it
in and you can see it's cre transcript
of everything that I said so we can
watch it back when people are color
grading when
PE I do this all the time like what I'm
actually recording has so many mistakes
stops and starts but gling understands
that it knows how YouTubers talk and it
can remove all of these dead ends and
these words that don't go anywhere so
you can see at this beginning here I
started to say okay to show you then I
repeated myself and I said to show you
how gling works it's already cut that
out so if I turn on skip cuts and I hit
play I basically already have a fully
edited YouTube video and I didn't do
anything it understands the context and
it really gets things right A lot of the
time now the only step I need to do is I
kind of proofread it and make sure that
it's not screwing anything up like here
I changed my phrasing I said first when
people are color grading then the next
time I said when people try to correct
log footage it didn't realize those were
the same sentence so I can just click
this little cut and now I've removed
that whole line and I just kind of
proofread the whole thing then I'm ready
to go if I want I can also change the
paste so it can remove more or less
pauses as I go through so like I could
crank it up and it's going to remove
pauses between words I don't want to go
that fast I want to keep it pretty
natural and when I'm done and I hit
export it's got a ton of different
options so this isn't just for Final Cut
Pro but that is what I'm going to use
today and I'm going to select multicam
because there is a really great trick
here in the same Library I will import
XML open it up and I've got a a edited
timeline all ready to go but what's
great is I can now open up that multicam
add some different angles so now if I
open up my multic cam editor I can just
cut between different angles as it's
playing gling has already edited the
whole thing for me so all I got to do
now is choose the angles this is so
insanely powerful check out gling in the
link in the description below and thanks
again to gling for sponsoring this video
so back to getting the rest of our
timeline graded I'll select my one clip
that looks good command C to copy then
command a to select all of my timeline
I'm going to use command click to
deselect that one clip since it's
already graded then I press command
shift and V this is going to paste
whatever attributes you want across all
of these clips so take a look at it make
sure they make sense you might have done
some slow motion and stuff I don't want
to paste that I don't want to paste
volume I'm looking to paste the color
effects across everything hit paste and
now my whole timeline has a basic color
grade done to it but let's say you made
a mist AK I changed my mind all the time
so for example I had lowered the
exposure on that one clip that didn't
need to be everywhere so let's reset all
of that and now I need to adjust them
all again this is a super helpful
shortcut I learned that I'm constantly
putting to you so I'm going to command C
to copy again select all including the
one that I'm on right now and I'm going
to press command shift X this brings up
remove attributes how helpful is that so
I'm just going to remove all of those
effects that I just applied everything
is now back to log I've still copied
things sitting in my clipboard and I can
press command shift V again and paste
those
attributes back in and now everything is
caligor and I've got completely neutral
primaries no adjustments have been made
so now I could go like one clip at a
time decide that needs to be warmed up
so needs to be darkened let's say also
warmed up a little I don't even know if
I do that it's like at a very different
clip okay this one's missing maybe some
contrast and it's a little cool so bring
down Shadows a little little bring back
the saturation warm it up a little
whatever you need to do now you can
apply it on a clip by clip basis now
let's say you want to take the look a
little bit further make it look a bit
more filmic you can select a clip again
we're going to drag another custom let
on top and there's a lot of lets out
there that can be applied over top of
Rec 709 so I have a bunch in my pack
that'll really push the colors around
they're not like corrective so this can
happen afterwards and they're usually a
little too strong so dial them back to
maybe like 50% and then you've got
something kind of interesting so you'd
want to do the step before you've
applied it to everything so now I would
copy select all command shift X command
shift paste and now everything would
have that same filmic look applied on
top and actually there's another common
way I do this so I'm going to delete
that custom let you're going to have to
add an adjustment layer for some reason
these aren't built in the Final Cut but
if you just Google them or look in the
description I'll provide a link you can
download them and you'll just drag it on
top of everything so if I zoom out I can
look at the whole timeline make sure
it's applied to everything put a custom
L on top of that adjustment layer and
look at that the whole timeline now has
that same filmic look applied to it so
that's how you work with appal log in
Final Cut Pro I really hope this was
helpful to you guys let me know if you
have any questions all the links are in
the description below thanks again to
gling for sponsoring this video and I'll
see you guys in the next one
[Music]